when we studied the philosophy of
Emanuel Kant I said that the revolution
in ideas that was precipitated by kant's
work had greater impact on American
civilization than our actual uh
government revolution of
1776 but if there's any philosopher
whose thinking had a greater impact on
the whole of Western civilization and in
a short period of time it would be that
of Carl Marx I mentioned that when I was
in high school there were two billion
people uh on the face of this Earth and
by 1965 the number of people who were
under the regime of communist government
and who lived behind the Iron Curtain
were two billion people that is the same
number of people who populated the
entire our globe in 1957 just a few
years later uh as the world progressed
in its uh population uh it reached that
same number of those who were uh under
the tyranny of marxist governments and
so if we think that ideas have
consequences then we certainly see that
manifest in the philosophical work of
Carl Marx but we also understand from
the beginning of our study that not only
are there consequences to ideas and that
ideas shape events but also events have
the same reciprocal tendency to spawn
new ideas and if you look at the
biography of KL Marx you will see
something dramatic that took place in
his childhood that had a tremendous
impact on his thinking and consequently
on the whole world when he was a boy he
was born into a Jewish Family in Germany
and his father was a prosperous
Merchant and the family had to move to
another city and when they moved to the
new city the city was dominated by
members of the Lutheran Church and for
business
purposes Carl Marx's father joined the
Lutheran Church uh because he thought
that it would help in his business and
this had a tremendous impact on this
young boy he was completely
disillusioned by this and saw in that
experience that what was driving his own
family and his own personal environments
was not religion or faith or
ideas but
economics and he never forgot that and
as he went to England later on and
studied in the British Museum and sat
there and contemplated the history of
the world he had been a student of
Frederick Hegel and he agreed with
hegel's idea that history moved in a
dialectic process but he disagreed with
his mentor who developed IDE idealistic
uh materialism and Marx produced his
theory of
dialectical
materialism that is he said
that history is driven by the conflict
not of spiritual ideas or logical
Concepts but rather through the very
real concrete impulses of material
concerns particularly with respect to uh
The Clash of economic systems and he
said the way in which this manifests
itself outwardly in the the shaping of
society and of world culture is in what
he called the class struggle and looking
back over the course of history he saw
that people had gone through various
stages of
transition from the feudal system of the
Middle Ages to The Agrarian economy that
followed it and then later on into the
industrial
revolution which provoked a crisis
according to Marks that reach deep into
the human Spirit you know that the
traditional way in which we've defined
the uniqueness of man is to describe man
as Homo
sapiens which means man the wise that is
our uniqueness has been rooted and
grounded in our intellectual capacity
and our ability to reflect upon our own
existence and that sort of thing well
Marx rejected that view of man and said
that the proper definition for the
uniqueness of the human race should be
found in this expression homo
Faber you understand that in the
Germanic
world uh a a a factory is called a
fabriek and the fabrique is the place
where things are manufactured or are
made
and so that's the basic word behind this
and Homo Faber means literally man the
maker or man the
worker and what Marx was saying at this
point is that what defines our human
existence where we eat and drink and
sleep is centrally related to our work
whenever you meet somebody for the first
time you ask them three questions you
ask them their name where they live and
then you ask them what do you do and
that expresses the concern that we have
to identify our own existence in terms
of our vocation or in terms of our labor
now Marx as he analyzed the movement of
History said that our deepest existence
is rooted in our work and that what what
happened with the industrial Revol the
Industrial Revolution and the uh
conquest of capitalism as an economic
system particularly in the Western World
produced in the human Spirit a profound
alienation and it's the alienation of
the individual from the fruit of his
labor and he saw this as a crisis that
would uh would bring about radical
changes in the future structures of
society unlike the philosophers of
history that had preceded him such as
Hegel who looked for history to flow out
out of this dialectical process through
a built-in evolutionary system by which
history just happens to move by
invisible laws in in a given Direction
Marx came to the conclusion that if we
can see where Society ought to be and is
not there that is if we can Envision a
better world order than we presently
enjoy we should not wait for the
impersonal forces of evolutionary
history to bring that about but we need
to take action to change the given
structures of the day and so he
advocated the use of violence to bring
about the Improvement of man's economic
condition you've seen the slogan arbite
mry labor makes free and workers of the
World Unite all having its roots in the
uh impetus of Marx's philosophy where he
encouraged the proletariat the working
class to rise up in Revolution against
the owner ownership class to bring about
a new world order through violent
revolution which revolutions occurred
with great rapidity in the earlier part
of the 20th century that brought about
dramatic changes to uh the Society of
this
world part of this alienation from his
labor that Mark spoke of was this in a
rural economy in an agrarian economy the
farmer is more or less self-sufficient
much more self-sufficient than in an
industrialized society and he owns his
own tools but most
significantly he enjoys the fruit of his
own
labor when the transition came from that
kind of an environment to an
industrialized environment then people
began to work for
wages where they did not participate in
the ownership of the company or the
factory in which they work and did not
own the fruit of their
labor and so Marx saw this modern system
as a reinvention of
slavery not the kind of slavery that the
feudal surf lived under under the
military leadership of uh the barons of
that day but now it was a slavery
imposed by the factory owners the owner
of the excuse me the owner of The
Company Store for example who gave a
pittance by way of
salary to the worker and to the laborer
but the the great bulk of the profit
from this industry went to the
owner and as a result people were cut
off from the fruit of the their labor
and also at this point Marx raised a
serious challenge against the
capitalistic view of
value that according to capitalism the
laws of Economics that rule are the
basic laws of supply and demand and what
drives the value of goods and services
up obviously is scarcity more than
anything else
and so one of the reasons why the
managerial class earns so much more
money than the working class is
because the uh knowledge that they bring
to the job is scarce and it has a
greater uh value per person in the
success of the capitalistic Enterprise
that is people who have entrepreneurial
skills and gifts who are are
knowledgeable technicians and so on get
higher wages than unskilled laborers
because they're uh there's a competitive
Marketplace and their scarcity of
knowledge and gifts and talents drives
up their value as wage earners in the
marketplace just as the scarcity of
goods drives up the price of goods in
the marketplace and over against that
way of doing things
Marx created or emphasized what he
called the labor
theory of
value that the way in which wages should
be paid is on the value of the labor
that is brought rather than on the
scarcity of it that it's the hard toil
of the man in the blast furnace that
really makes it possible to produce
steel and his great energy cost and and
sweat and toil should be the subject of
a much greater reward because the value
of work is intrinsically related to the
effort that is
produced now also in this understanding
of things Marx saw that the key
advantage that the owners had over the
workers was that the owners owned and
controlled the means of
production now we say that that whoever
owns the tools owns the game when I was
a kid and we played baseball we didn't
have organized baseball games we didn't
have official umpires and so we had to
referee as it were ourselves among
ourselves and if there were a dis if
there happened to be a disputed call at
first base I'm I say I'm safe the other
guy says out and one team all agrees
that he's out and the other team all say
he safe who's de sdes well it would
usually come down to this it's my bat
it's my ball I'm safe because without me
there is no baseball game because I own
the means of production I own the
tools and he understood that the
invention of tools is what propelled the
world into the Industrial Age because
what tools do is save labor they are
labor saving devices and that tools have
the unique ability to bring about
exponential increases in production you
take your uh your front lawn and you
want to uh to keep your front lawn
manicured there are different ways that
you can do it
you could go out there with a pair of
scissors and cut each blade of grass
individually to keep your lawn manicured
it would be very inexpensive in terms of
the tool that you use but at the same
time it would be a labor intensive and
time
consuming now you can improve your
productivity in cutting your grass by
getting a more sophisticated tool you
could produce buy you could perhaps buy
a push lawn mower and do the job in much
less uh time with much less effort than
you would with a pair of scissors and
but however to do that costs more money
because the lawn mower costs more than
the pair of scissors and then you can go
beyond that to a power mower and reduce
your time even further and your effort
even further but your expense goes up
for that particular tool and you can go
to the next level of a riding lawn mower
which makes it all the quicker and and
easier on you but more expensive and so
the point is that as tools become more
sophisticated they have the capacity to
increase production radically you take
the American Farmer and compare him to a
third world Farmer and the two farmers
may be of the same physical strength and
the same native
intelligence but one produces a 100
times more wheat than the other one and
the basic reason is that the American
Farmer has the sophisticated tools and
equipment to increase his production
where the man in the third world is
using a m a mule and a wooden plow
perhaps and so Marx understood how the
means of production Drive economic
growth and prosperity but the problem he
saw in all of this alienation was it is
the ownership class who owns the tool
tools and because they own the tools
they have the power to exploit the
workers they hire at their wages but all
of the all of the profit goes to the
owner and this produces enmity
alienation and the class struggle you
can see this right now in professional
sports where the players are saying I
want High salary because without me
nobody comes to the stadium and the
owner says wait a minute I'm the one
that invested in this in this Venture in
the first place I'm the one who took the
risk it's my capital that made this
possible and and not only that but the
value of this sport has been contributed
to by all those who came before you to
build up this franchise why do you think
that this group should suddenly get all
of the reap the profits when they
haven't put the expenses in at the other
on on the other side are saying but wait
a minute because of our skill in our
labor you're reaping hundreds of
millions of dollars and I want a piece
of it and so you have conflict you have
lockouts you have strikes you have all
of that going on because you're having a
struggle over economics and a kind of
class
Warfare and so what Marx called for was
the ownership of the means of production
by the state to get r rid of private
ownership of the means of production
because he believed by the states owning
the tools and owning the means of
Productions then there would be a great
leveling of benefits to all of the
people and that everybody would profit
equally from the the uh welfare of the
state from each according to his ability
to each according to his need and but
for that to happen takes Evolution
because the structures that are in place
in capitalistic societies according to
Marx are
established really on the basis of
economic vested interest and a whole
superstructure of that Society is built
on these economic forces and they are
designed in order to safeguard and
perpetuate the V Ed interests of the
ruling class the two institutions that
Marx criticized most uh radically were
law and
religion he said that we the capitalist
Society say that they build their legal
structure on the basis of some
Transcendent concept of Justice where
Lady Justice has a blindfold and natural
law dominates and he said no that's not
how it really happens what really
happens is that the legal structure of a
given Society will always reflect the
vested interests of the ruling class
that is the laws will favor the rich and
disenfranchise the poor they will favor
the owner and be harmful to the worker
and so the idea of a just Society based
on natural law is a mythological concept
cep that is perpetrated by the fraud of
the uh ruling classes and this is seen
all the more
forcibly in the uh presence of religion
you've heard the phrase that wasn't
originated with Marx but was used by
Marx and his followers that religion is
the opiate of the masses that is that
religion is used by the ruling class to
put the working class which is always in
the majority asleep to cause them to be
dulled and numbed to their pain uh we
might use the American uh cotton
Plantation during the earlier period of
our history that used slave labor and
the slaves were encouraged to enjoy
their religion and to see the sing their
songs which
featured a future reward based upon
present Obed
obedience it's Swing Low Sweet Chariot
come and forth to carry me home I looked
over Jordan and what did I see a band of
angels coming after me the idea was keep
your eyes on Heaven because you're not
going to get anything here but if you
behave yourself and be a good slave then
when you die you'll go to heaven and God
will reward you there and so Mark said
that religion is invented by the ru
schooling class to maintain control over
the masses and is used as a tool to
exploit them that's why he wanted to get
rid of not only the the false juridical
structures of capitalistic Society but
also of the religions the organized
religion that was used as a tool by the
owners to keep the workers in line now
his own philosophical structure had its
religious elements it had its Saints and
its Heroes that were virtually adored
and worshiped and he gave them all a
future promise a utopian eschatology
where for Marks Heaven would be heaven
on Earth that would be realized by a
classless society in which the free
development of each individual person
would translate into to the free
development of all there's as I said
there's probably been no philosophical
system that has had such a rapid and
radical impact on people's lives in the
history of the West and the East than
Marxism and yet at the same time there's
probably never been a philosophy that
promised more and produced less than
this one no philosophy that's plunged
more people into such abject misery as
this one had because Marx's theories
violated the basic laws of of growth in
prosperity and wealth for people and it
has proven to be an unqualified disaster
and probably the last Bastion of Marxism
left in this world today as some
commentators have said is the American
University
system